Guide to the Goldwin Smith papers, 1819-1921,
Smith, Goldwin papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Goldwin Smith papers, 1819-1921, 1844-1915 (bulk).
14-17-134
Smith, Goldwin,
30 cubic ft.,
>Correspondence, Manuscripts, Newspapers, Microfilm, Printed Materials, Publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence; scrapbooks; journals; clippings; addresses; translations; drafts, manuscripts, and articles; printed copies of works by or about Goldwin Smith
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Historian, journalist, professor at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence; scrapbooks; journals; clippings; addresses; translations; drafts, manuscripts, and articles; printed copies of works by or about Goldwin Smith; obituaries and memorials; photographs; personal correspondence and a few family papers; and materials gathered by Smith's secretary Theodore Arnold Haultain for a series of volumes he planned to publish on the works of Goldwin Smith.
Included is correspondence of Lord Ashbourne, Charles F. Benjamin, S.H.J. Böhme, Henri Bourassa (Canadian M.P.), John Bright, James Bryce, Joseph Chamberlain, W. Bourke Cochran, Sir Charles Dilke, Lord Farrer, W.E. Gladstone, George M. Grant, M.E. Grant-Duff, F. Greenwood, Earl Grey, James J. Hill, Hon. H.G. Joly, James Laister, Lord Lansdowne, Sir John A. MacDonald, Herbert E. Millholen (city editor, NEW YORK EVENING POST), Lord Minto, Lord Morley, Horace Plunkett, Anna P. Pruyn, John M. Robertson, Lord Rosebery, Charles B. Spahr (Anti-Imperialist League), James Strachey (editor, SPECTATOR), Professor James Sully, Phillips Thompson, Professor Tyndall, General J.H. Wilson, Mrs. Emma Winkworth, and Viscount Wolseley.
Goldwin Smith's correspondence with members of the faculty and administration of Cornell University not only reveals his concern for that institution, but also relates to literary and political subjects. Included is correspondence of George Lincoln Burr, Hiram Corson, George W. Curtis, Willard Fiske, Jacob Gould Schurman, Moses Coit Tyler, and Andrew D. White. A series of letters written between 1868 and 1870 to George Waring in England records Smith's initial reactions to the new university and toward American places, people, and attitudes. The University of Toronto and Queens University in Kingston are the subjects of correspondence with J.W. Flavelle and George M. Grant.
A.H. Beesly, A.V. Dicey, C.H. Firth, E.A. Freeman, George Otto Trevelyan, and P. Villari are among the historians who corresponded with Goldwin Smith; their letters comment upon current social and political trends and events, as well as upon their work as historians. Among other correspondents are Charles Francis Adams, the Duke of Argyll, Matthew Arnold, W.J. Ashley, General Lord Bryce (NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW), Andrew Carnegie, Lord Chief Justice Coleridge, D.C. Gilman, General Sir Fred Middleton, Julian Pauncefote, Viscount Peel, and Carl Schurz.
There are also some family papers, including journals of Smith's mother, Elizabeth Breton Smith.
Collection also includes Goldwin Smith's academic robe from Oxford and hood from McMasters University.
English, Canadian, and American political issues (ca. 1880-1910) dominate the correspondence of Goldwin Smith: the possibility of a Canada-United States union, commercial or political; free trade vs. protection; party maneuvering in all three countries; the problem of the French Canadian element; the Irish Home Rule struggle; local and municipal government reform; imperialism, particularly as it was manifested in the Boer and Spanish-American Wars; the yellow press; the women's suffrage movement; the Jew in the modern national state; socialism and the increasing importance of labor groups in government; British policy toward Russia; the Canadian-Pacific Railroad and its influence on government; and related topics.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Smith, Goldwin, 1823-1910.; Adams, Charles Francis, 1835-1915.; Argyll, John Douglas Sutherland Campbell, Duke of, 1845-1914.; Arnold, Matthew, 1822-1888.; Ashbourne, Edward Gibson, Baron, 1837-1913.; Ashley, W. J. (William James), 1860-1927.; Beesly, A. H. (Augustus Henry), 1839-1909.; Benjamin, Charles F.; Böhme, S. H. J.; Bourassa, Henri, 1868-1952.; Bright, John, 1811-1889.; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922.; Bryce, Lloyd.; Burr, George Lincoln, 1857-1938.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.; Chamberlain, Joseph, 1836-1914.; Cochran, W. Bourke.; Coleridge, John Duke Coleridge, Baron, 1820-1894.; Corson, Hiram, 1828-1911.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Dicey, A. V. (Albert Venn), 1835-1922.; Dicey, A. V. (Albert Venn), 1835-1922; Dilke, Charles Wentworth, Sir, 1843-1911.; Farrer, Thomas Henry Farrer, Baron, 1819-1899.; Firth, C. H. (Charles Harding), 1857-1936.; Fiske, Willard, 1831-1904.; Flavelle, Joseph, 1858-1939.; Freeman, Edward A. (Edward Augustus), 1823-1892.; Gilman, Daniel C. (Daniel Coit), 1831-1908.; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898.; Grant Duff, Mountstuart E. (Mountstuart Elphinstone), Sir, 1829-1906.; Grant, George Monro, 1835-1902.; Greenwood, Frederick, 1830-1909.; Grey, Henry George Grey, Earl, 1802-1894.; Grey, Henry George Grey, Earl, 1802-1894; Hill, James J. (James Jerome), 1838-1916.; Joly, H. G.; Laister, James.; Lansdowne, Henry Charles Keith Petty-FitzMaurice, Marquess of, 1845-1927.; Macdonald, John A. (John Alexander), 1815-1891.; Middleton, Fred, Sir.; Millholen, Herbert E.; Minto, Gilbert John Murray Kynynmond Elliot, Earl of, 1845-1914.; Morley, John, 1838-1923.; Pauncefote, Julian, 1828-1902.; Peel, Robert, 1788-1850.; Plunkett, Horace Curzon, Sir, 1854-1932.; Pruyn, Anna P.; Robertson, J. M. (John Mackinnon), 1856-1933.; Rosebery, Archibald Philip Primrose, Earl of, 1847-1929.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906.; Smith, Elizabeth Breton.; Spahr, Charles B. (Charles Barzillai), 1860-1904.; Stachey, James.; Sully, James, 1842-1923.; Thomson, Phillips.; Trevelyan, George Otto, 1838-1928.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893.; Villari, Pasquale, 1827-1917.; Waring, George E., (George Edwin), Jr. 1833-1898.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Wilson, James Harrison, 1837-1925.; Winkworth, Emma; Winkworth, Emma.; Wolseley, Garnet Wolseley, Viscount, 1833-1913.; Wolseley, Garnet Wolseley, Viscount, 1833-1913; Canadian-Pacific Railroad.; Cornell University -- Administration.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Cornell University; Queens University (Kingston, Ont.); Queen's University (Kingston, Ont.); University of Toronto; University of Toronto.; Spanish-American War (1898)
Subjects:
Politics, Practical -- United States.; Politics, Practical -- England.; Politics, Practical -- Canada.; Protectionism.; French-Canadians.; Imperialism.; Sensationalism in journalism.; Colleges and universities -- United States.; Colleges and universities -- Canada.; Women -- Suffrage -- United States.; Jews -- History -- 1789-1945.; Labor unions -- Political activity.; Socialism.; Railroads -- Canada.; English literature.; College teachers.; Historians.; Journalists.; College teachers; Diplomatic relations; English literature; Ethnic relations; French-Canadians; Historians; Imperialism; Jews; Journalists; Labor unions -- Political activity; Management; Manners and customs; Political science; Politics, Practical; Protectionism; Railroads; Sensationalism in journalism; Universities and colleges -- Faculty; Women -- Suffrage
Places:
United States -- Politics and government.; United States -- Social life and customs.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Canada.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; United States -- History -- 1849-1877.; United States -- History -- 1865-1921.; Canada -- Ethnic relations.; Canada -- Politics and government.; Canada -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Great Britain -- Politics and government.; England -- Foreign relations -- Russia.; Ireland -- Politics and government.; Canada; England; Great Britain; Ireland; Russia; United States
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Other Finding Aids:
PDF of item-level lists for boxes available.
Link to the printed microfilm collection guide. PDF file. Contains additional biographical information.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  Letters copied from other collections for the microfilm are interfiled
  - Correspondence, August 1844-March 1866 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, April 1866- December 1873 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, January 1874-June 1881 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, July 1881-December 1887 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, January 1888-September 1892 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, October 1892-August 1894 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, September 1894-December 1895 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, January 1896-May1897 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, June 1897-August 1898 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, September 1898-November 15, 1899 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, November 16, 1899-October 1900 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, November 1900-November 1901 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, December 1901-October 1902 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, November 1902-October 1903 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, November 1903-August 1904 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, September 1904-March 1905 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, April 1905-December 1905 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, January 1906-August 1906 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, September 1906-April 1907 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, May1907-February 1908 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, March 1908-November 1908 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, December 1908-June 1909 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, July 1909-December 1909 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, January 1910-1921 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 25)
- Series II. Manuscripts, Printed Material, Clippings, and Biographical Information
  PDF of item-level lists for boxes 41-53 available via link at the top of this guide.
  - Lists of pamphlets and "Weekly Sun" articles, of contributions to the "Canadian Monthly", MS fragments, and a list of correspondents for a proposed book of Smith letters prepared by TA Haultain (Box 25)
  - Index and bibliographical cards prepared by Haultain (Box 26)
  - MS of introduction and much of the text of "The United States", written in the hand of Charles F. Benjamin (Box 27)
  - Typescript of a projected volume of Smith letters "comprising chiefly letters to his American friends" (Box 27)
  - Partial scrapbook of clippings in England, 1882 (Box 27)
  - Two loose-leaf typescript copies of a Hewett bibliography of Smith works (Box 27)
  - Carbon copy of the membership of the National Continental Union League (Box 27)
  - Galley proof of "My Memory of Gladstone", and others of the same work (Box 27)
  - Manuscripts for articles (Box 27)
    Includes "The Early Days of Cornell" typescript, "Abraham Lincoln" typescripts and clipping, "Chatham", "Cromwell", "Labour and Socialism", "Peace with Justice", "Guesses at the Riddle of Existence", and miscellaneous fragments
  - MS of Goldwin Smith address at the laying of the cornerstone of Goldwin Smith Hall, bound in red leather, 1904 (Box 28)
  - Letter from Smith to Schurman (1903) and accompanying letter from Dean of Arts and Sciences (1918), 1903, 1918 (Box 28)
  - Letter registers recoding letters and MSS sent by Haultain, 1891, 1893-1900 (Box 28)
    See also box 38
  - Notebooks with translations from the classics (Box 28)
    Related to material in box 35
  - Scrapbook of press clippings, January 1889-July 1990 (Box 28)
  - Scrapbook of contributions to periodicals, 1908-1909 (Box 28)
  - Portfolio of early studies in English history on: Athelstan; Becket; Henry I, II, and III; Simon de Montfors; Edward I, II and III; William the Conqueror, and more (Box 28)
  - Rough draft and proofs of a projected history of England up to the Restoration (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, including reviews of "Canada and the Canadian Question", 1893 (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook of clipped reviews of "The United States", including some letters of criticism (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, 1894-1895 (Box 29)
  - Scrapbook of clippings on Canadian events, including reviews and comments on "The Bystander", 1880 (Box 30)
  - Scrapbook of Smith contributions to "The Week", December 6, 1883-January 15, 1885 (Box 30)
  - Bundle of copies of "The Week", 1885-1890 (Box 30)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, mostly Smith letters to newspapers, June 4, 1890-July 8, 1891 (Box 30)
  - "From a Trans-Atlantic Point of View", Smith article against Home Rule (Box 30)
  - Clippings preserved by G. Mercer Adam, but not containing the signature of Smith (Box 30)
  - Typed manuscript of Smith's "Reminiscences" (Box 31)
  - Chapters of a book on the United Kingdom (Box 31)
  - Manuscript of "The Present and Future of Religion", a projected volume of contributions to the "New York Sun" (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous articles and lectures (Box 31)
    Including The Schism in the Anglo-Saxon Race, The Weak Point of the Elective System, Article on Froude's "Divorce of Catherine of Aragon", a response to a toast at a Psi Upsilon meeting, and a lecture on The Old University through the Ages
  - Notes and copies of exam questions used by Trinity College, and proof sheets of exams prepared by Smith at Trinity, 1884, 1887-1888 (Box 31)
  - Selections from "The Bystander", chosen by Haultain with the intention of publishing them, 1880-1890 (Box 32)
  - Draft of Smith's "Reminiscences" (Box 32)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings by or about Smith, 1888-1893, 1904-1910 (Box 33)
  - Bound group of clippings withdrawn from Cornell Library shelves (Box 33)
  - "Bystander" articles from the original files of the "Toronto Weekly Sun", 1904-1910 (Box 34)
    Presented to Cornell by Walter Dymond Gregory, 1939
  - 12 MS notebooks "Translation of Arundel Manuscripts" (Box 35)
  - 14 MS notebooks with Smith's translations of poetry, classical school work, and political and historical fragments (Box 35)
  - Notebook with printed pages, MS notes and typed copies of correspondence regarding Smith and St. George's, 1894 (Box 35)
  - Press clippings, mostly reviews of Smith's published works, 1894-1896, 1904-1913 (Box 36)
  - Press clippings, further reviews, 1893-1894, 1897, 1902, 1907 (Box 37)
  - Manuscripts, ca. 1900-1910 (Box 37)
    Including "Party Government", "The Future of Poetry", In the Court of History", "Nationality and Empire", "White Man's Burden", and the first four chapters of a school history of the US
  - Volume II of Haultain's republication plan, entitled "Historical and Political America" (Box 37)
  - Smith's notebooks (Box 38)
    Lists of Oxford students, ethics, Greek, and Latin composition, Essay on murders of Caesar and Marat, address books and pocket diaries
  - Letter registers, 1901-1910 (Box 38)
  - Waterman Hewett notebooks, mostly Smith's bibliographic notes and Hewett's travel itinerary, 1913-1915 (Box 38)
    Includes file cards of references to Smith in works of other writers
  - Early manuscripts (Box 39)
    Notebooks on England, list of Cornell students and notes to Howell, Bibliographic notes on religious parties
  - Later manuscripts, 1895-1910 (Box 39)
    "The Bases of the Empire", "The Founder of Christendom", "Progress or Revolution", "Labour and Socialism", "Unionism is not Socialism", "Socialism in Action"
  - Literary articles assembled by Haultain for republication (Box 39)
  - Journal of Smith's mother Elizabeth Breton Smith (Box 40)
    Includes records of births, deaths, family events, journeys to Paris, English Lakes, and Welshpool
  - Lectures on English history, outlines, and fragments on Athenaeum Club stationary (Box 40)
  - Bills and Receipts, notes accompanying payment for articles, proofs and printed articles and letters to editors, 1885-1897 (Box 40)
  - Manuscripts (Box 43)
  - Articles, pamphlets, and autograph address at cornerstone laying of Sage College (Box 44)
  - Manuscripts (Box 44)
  - Copies of Smith's editorials in the "Weekly Sun" (Box 45)
  - Two scrapbooks of "Bystander" columns, plus pages of other scrapbooks (Box 46)
  - New Zealand clippings, 1902 (Box 46)
  - Clippings on Smith after death (Box 46)
  - "Bystander" magazine, 1889-1890 (Box 46)
  - Manuscripts, Book of tracts (Box 46)
  - Smith pamphlets and articles clipped from periodicals, written by Smith, and many other clipped articles (Box 46)
  - "Bystander" column clippings, 1896-1903 (Box 47)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings, Hewett's bibliography of Smith's writings, draft of "The United Kingdom" (Box 48)
  - Project for reprint publication by Haultain (Box 49)
  - Clippings (Box 49)
  - Manuscripts and clippings (Box 50)
  - Theodore Arnold Haultain correspondence, 1893-1905 (Box 51)
  - Theodore Arnold Haultain correspondence, 1906-1913 (Box 52)
  - Photographs (Box 53)
    The Grange, Smith, marble bust of Smith's wife, cartoons from Oxford of Smith
  - Clippings, Smith's will copy, list of Smith's works at Art Gallery in Toronto, and photocopy of letter and medallion of Napoleon (Box 53)
  - Printed pamphlets, 1845-1889 (Box 41)
  - Printed material by Goldwin Smith, 1890-1907 (Box 42)
  - Printed material, 1855-1910 (Box 42)
  - Pamphlets and printed items (Box 46)